<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A jury-man's judgement upon the case of Lieut. Col. John Lilburn: proving, by well-grounded arguments, both to his own and every jury-man's conscience, that they may not, cannot, ought not finde him guilty upon the Act of Parliament made for his banishment, and to be a felon for returning into England. That if any should or shall be tempted or misled so to do, they are notorious murtherers by the law of England, it being the worst of crimes that is done by colour of law. And, that it is as great a wickedness for any, (either judges, or sheriffs, or any other person) to have a hand in his death upon that Act, as wilfully to murther him.</title>
            <author>Jury-man.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 36 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 8 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A87439</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99863555</idno>
  <idno type="VID">115760</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240951984</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing J1214</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E702_6</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R203699</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99863555</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-99863555e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A87439)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 115760)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 108:E702[6])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A jury-man's judgement upon the case of Lieut. Col. John Lilburn: proving, by well-grounded arguments, both to his own and every jury-man's conscience, that they may not, cannot, ought not finde him guilty upon the Act of Parliament made for his banishment, and to be a felon for returning into England. That if any should or shall be tempted or misled so to do, they are notorious murtherers by the law of England, it being the worst of crimes that is done by colour of law. And, that it is as great a wickedness for any, (either judges, or sheriffs, or any other person) to have a hand in his death upon that Act, as wilfully to murther him.</title>
                  <author>Jury-man.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>15, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1653]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Imprint from Wing.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "June. 22. 1653".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="personal_name">Lilburne, John, 1614?-1657.</term>
               <term type="topical_term">Detention of persons --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-06 </date>
            <label>John Latta </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-06 </date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="treatise">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:115760:1"/>
            <head>A Jury-mans JUDGEMENT Upon the CASE of Lieut. Col. JOHN LILBURN: Proving, By well-grounded ARGUMENTS, both to his own and every Jury-man's CONSCIENCE,</head>
            <argument>
               <p>
                  <hi>That they may not, cannot, ought not finde him guilty upon the Act of Parliament made for his Banishment, and to be a Felon for returning into</hi> England.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>That if any should or shall be tempted or misled so to do, they are notorious murtherers by the Law of</hi> England, <hi>it being the worst of Crimes that is done by colour of Law.</hi> And,</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>That it is as great a wickedness for any, (either Judges, or She<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riffs, or any other person) to have a hand in his death upon that Act, as wilfully to murther him.</hi>
               </p>
            </argument>
            <p>COme, my dear Friends and loving Country-men, we the good men of <hi>England</hi> are continually called forth by Law to judge and to determine of men in all causes; amongst which, many are more difficult and weighty then others; and some so rare and seldome heard of, that if we take not very good heed, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sider
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:115760:2"/>things very well beforehand, and come substantially furnished and provided with sound and well-grounded consciences, and with clear and prepared mindes, free from fear, hope, or favour, in stead of judging others, we our selves may become as castawayes, and stand in the sight of God our Creator and judge of all men, no better then the vilest Reprobates and Murtherers.</p>
            <p>And truly, if ever there were a case of a rare and seldome heard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of nature, certainly the present case of Leiut. Col. <hi>John Lilburne</hi> is such; for although to such as look but upon the outside of things, there seems no great matter in it, which concerns his Jury-men to judge of, most men supposing that all which is required of us to do, is but to observe and to consider the evidence, proving that single per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son to be that <hi>John Lilburne</hi> that was banished by the Act, and that it is the very same that is returned, and so that being soon proved, from us to pronounce him guilty, upon which, death as a fellon is certain to proceed: though it be very likely this is all his prosecutors will urge upon us as our duty, yet we who are to answer for our selves to God, and not to them, must finde that there is a greater weight lying upon us in this cause then so, nor must we so easily be made instrumental to fulfil the wills of men; for whatever the most Learned or Eloquent man may say, the very life of this man. Leiut. Col. <hi>Lilburne</hi> lyes charged upon us, nor can he suffer death as a felon, except we finde and pronounce him guilty; so that except we are fully satisfied in our consciences, that he hath committed and stands before us charged, and is legally proved to have committed some crime, which in the known Law of <hi>England</hi> and the very nature of the offence is felony, and justly deserves to dye for it, with what conscience can any of us pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce him guilty? shall we bring in our verdict guilty, because he is <hi>John Lilburne</hi> returned from banishment contrary to an Act, that makes his return felony? and must our verdict usher in his death, and so as that he cannot dye except we do it? and shall we be so blinde and sottish as to do it, before we are satisfied in our consciences both of the lawfulness of the Parliaments making such an Act and of the heynousness of the crime committed by <hi>John Lilburne,</hi> upon which they made it? No, my brethren, God forbid that we should do this great wickedness, and so fin against God: we must be as careful, and are as highly concerned to be satisfied in our understandings of the
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:115760:2"/>Parliaments authority to make such an Act; and that Master <hi>Lil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burne</hi> hath committed a crime and so proved here in his presence, that by the true Law of England is felony, as we are to be satisfied that this is that <hi>John Lilburne:</hi> for if the former be not as cleer to us as the latter, and we pronounce him guilty and he dye upon it, how can we by all the art in the world be excused from being his mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therers? Wherefore, dear friends let us with all meekness and upright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness of heart and in the fear of God, as such who know and believe that we must all appear before the judgement-seat of Christ, there to render a most strict account for such trusts as these; let us, I say, fit and prepare our selves, as by prayer, meditation, and by a due search into the true Laws and rights of our native country; and if upon a full and impartial examination we find him not guilty of such a crime as by our known Law is felony, &amp; for which we in our consciences (gui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by our Law) do judge that he ought not to suffer death, let us with the assistance of God, with all integrity pronounce him not guilty, not fearing in the least what man can do unto us.</p>
            <p>But that we may be grounded and established in our judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, let us take a view of Master <hi>Lilburne</hi>'s Case, and the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments dealing with him, and judge impartially thereupon: the truth whereof is this, for what was done was not in a corner, but as upon the house top; and every one knowes that the maine agent in the whole worke is Sir <hi>Arthur Haselrigg,</hi> who of late yeers grow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to be a mighty landed and powerful man in the Northen parts, and in the Bishoprick of <hi>Durham,</hi> where the family of the <hi>Lilburns</hi> have alwayes been of good esteem and repute as men of courage, and such as in all times opposed every arbitrary power, Sir <hi>Arthur</hi> finding them such, and not brooking their aptness to oppose him, took all occasions to manifest a spirit of enmity towards them.</p>
            <p>And amongst other things, Lieut. Col. <hi>Lilburne</hi> being a close prisoner in the Tower, and put very hard to it for want of monyes to maintaine his family, Sir <hi>Arthur</hi> takes advantage of his imprison<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and without any authority, makes seizure of some hundreds of pounds which was due to him from one in those parts; upon which Master <hi>Lilburne</hi> published this injustice of his in printed books, lamentably complaining thereof, but prevailed not.</p>
            <p>But in short time after, was ordered to a trial for his life at Guild<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hall,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:115760:3"/>which some conceived to proceed primarily from Sir <hi>Arthur,</hi> because there was a stop of building the Scaffolds for a week, in which time he came to <hi>London,</hi> being expected a week before.</p>
            <p>How matters were carried at that trial we all know what extreme earnestness there was in Master <hi>Prideaux</hi> the Atturney-General and in all the Judges to take away his life; and had not his Jury been men that feared God more then the faces of men, he had not escaped: but they left a good example to us, and to all Jury-men throughout <hi>England</hi> of an undaunted integrity.</p>
            <p>After this, Mr. <hi>Lilburn</hi> being at liberty, we all know he betook himself to assist such as had occasion, as a Counsellor in Causes de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pending either in the Legal Courts, or before Committees; and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongst many others, engaged as Counsel for one Mr. <hi>Primate,</hi> in recovery of a Colliary neer <hi>Newcastle</hi> upon <hi>Tyne;</hi> which having at some time before received some kinde of trial at the Committee in the North, where Sir <hi>Arthur</hi> was in some sort interessed, Upon com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaint made, the whole matter was brought before the Commissioners of Sequestration at Haberdashers Hall; where Sir <hi>Arthur</hi> daily ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared in opposition to Mr. <hi>Lilburn</hi> and <hi>Primate</hi> his Clyent, and where there was for many days very large reasonings, pleadings, and debatings and sometimes hot and tart, onely before a numerous peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple: <hi>Lilburn</hi> and his Clyent, and very many others that heard the same, being confident of right on their side, and that they had made it so apparent, that it could not be given against them.</p>
            <p>But, contrary to their expectation in conclusion, the major part of the Committee carried it clearly against them, Mr. <hi>Moyer</hi> the Chayr-man dissenting: upon which Mr. <hi>Lilburn</hi> and his Clyent be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing much moved thereat, immediately tender a Petition to the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment by way of Appeal from the judgement of that Committee, ur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging earnestly for a new Tryal: and as a ground of their desire to move the Parliament to condescend thereunto, their Petition impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, that the Committee was over-awed by Sir <hi>Arthur Haselrig;</hi> whereby, and by other indirect means, they were wrought to give Judgement as they did.</p>
            <p>Now this Petition being not presently received, they cause it to be printed, and Mr. <hi>Lilburn</hi> himself gives it to every member of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament. Upon which, the Parliament being moved, took great
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:115760:3"/>offence, being offended chiefly at the scandalizing of a member, by charging Sir <hi>Arthur</hi> with over-awing and the like in that Petition mentioned: next, for that the Petition was Printed before it was read by the House: and lastly, because of scandalizing certain members of the Committee of Haberdashers Hall, as having given an unjust Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in the Case. These three put together, making up the whole Crime that <hi>John Lilburn</hi> can possibly be guilty of, this being the ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>most that was layd to his Charge; which you are especially to note in this place, this being the first appearance of their displeasure, the Parliaments Sentence and Act for his 7000 <hi>l.</hi> Fine, perpetual Banish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and be taken as a Felon if he should return, having no other cause upon which they grounded the same, but from these three at most; all the rest of the proceedings which followed in the Chequer-Chamber, amounting to no more, but to prove that Mr. <hi>Lilburn</hi> was justly to be charged with scandalizing Sir <hi>Arthur Hazelrig,</hi> and divers Members of the Committee of Haberdashers Hall, and that in printing the Petition before the House had received and read it, he had broken the Priviledge of Parliament.</p>
            <p>As to the merit of the cause concerning the Colliary in question, the matter was heard again by the Committee appointed in the Chequer Chamber, where very many were again clearly of opinion that the right was on Mr. <hi>Primats</hi> side: and it is said that if some Parliament<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men then present at the whole debate, day after day might be heard, they would depose upon their oaths that the report made by the chair<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Mr. <hi>Hill</hi> the Lawyer, was no true report; but upon his report as it was the Parliament took for proved that Lieut. Col. <hi>John Lilburn</hi> had highly scandalized Sir <hi>Arthur,</hi> and divers members of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittee of <hi>Haberdashers</hi>-hall and had broken the priviledge of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, in printing and giving out copies of the Petition before the House had received and read it: And for those offences, did sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence him to pay 7000 <hi>l.</hi> between Sir <hi>Arthur Haslerig</hi> and the Members of <hi>Haberdashers</hi>-Hall, whom he had scandalized; and to be perpetually banished, and to be taken as a Felon if he should return; and make it an Act of Parliament accordingly: And who being now returned contrary to that Act, is certainly to die, if his Jury pronounce him guilty of the breach of that Act by his so returning. But is here a ground for our Consciences to be so far instrumental in his
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:115760:4"/>death, as to pronounce him guilty? guilty indeed is soon said, and a mans life is soon taken away, but it is not so soon answered, as un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>justly and unlawfully done: death indeed is the lawful punishment due to a Felon in <hi>England:</hi> but then a Felon is known to be so by a Felonious Crime: what it is, Jury-men do so well know, that though a man be indicted for Felony, they will not bring him in guilty there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, if they finde his Fact of less Nature; their Consciences being to be satisfied of the nature and demerit of the offence, and are not to pronounce guilty; so that the life of a man shall certainly be taken away thereupon, when they in their Consciences finde him guilty of a Fact, for which by the true Law of the Land, he ought not to die: no, the Law of <hi>England</hi> hath not placed Tryals by Juries to stand between men and death to so little purpose, as to pronounce men guilty without regard to the nature of the offence, or to what is to be inflicted thereupon.</p>
            <p>And where now lieth Mr. <hi>Lilburns</hi> Felonious crime? Is it, or ever was it Felony by the true Law of <hi>England,</hi> for any man to scandalize or slander a Parliament-man, or to scandalize Members of a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittee; or to break the unknown priviledges of a Parliament? or was it onely Felony for Mr. <hi>John Lilburn</hi> to do those things? none surely will imagine so for the Laws of <hi>England</hi> are generall, and that which is Felony for any one to do, is Felony for every one that doth it.</p>
            <p>Pray you friends let us see which of those offences would appear Felonious: admit Mr. <hi>Lilburn</hi> stood before us now indicted, for that he did feloniously affirm, that Sir <hi>Arthur Haslerig</hi> over-awed the Committee at <hi>Haberdashers</hi>-hall: and likewise feloniously slander<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed that Committee, by saying they gave an unjust judgement in <hi>Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mates</hi> Case; And likewise had feloniously broken the Priviledges of Parliament; admit all these had been punctually proved, could our Verdict have been that he is guilty of Felony? no, at no hand, nor for a world would we do it. Why? because our Law makes not such offences Felony: what then? could we have brought him in guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of Banishment? no, neither; our Law hath ordained no such pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nishment for such offences: what then? how are such offences to be punished? why friends, for such offences, thus: Sir <hi>Arthur</hi> concei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving himself slandered or scandalized by Mr. <hi>Lilburn,</hi> might have brought his Action at Common-Law; and upon proof made, have recovered good damages, as Juries commonly give, and so might
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:115760:4"/>any of the Commissioners of <hi>Haberdashers</hi>-hall; and may do yet: but if not proved, but on the contrary, that what they urged as slan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, were found truths, there's no offence. And for the breach of Priviledge of Parliament, it hath been so often spoken, and so little understood to have any dependance on the Law of <hi>England,</hi> that no man, neither Parliament-man nor other ever understood to define what they were; but have proved such as Prerogative was wont to be, <hi>viz.</hi> to make a man an offender (at pleasure) for a word, or for a thing that none but themselves could imagine to be offensive; as indeed, what can be in printing and publishing of a Petition before received or in the House? why should the matter of a Petition be dainty to be seen? but such things we have lived to see from Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, which had our forefathers seen, they would have said they had been the fruits rather of an imperious Court, then of a peoples Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament: but God forbid that the Jury-men of <hi>England</hi> should be so sottish, and blind-fold, as without examination to serve such Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liaments ends in taking away mens lives upon their Votes or Acts, evidently contrary to the known Law of the Land.</p>
            <p>And such, and no better, will prove this their Act for banishing of <hi>John Lilburn,</hi> it being indeed no Law, but is null and void in it self, because it is contrary to the known Law of the Land, for so are all Laws, though made by Parliament, if they are contrary to the stan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding Laws of the Nation.</p>
            <p>Now nothing in the world is more known then this in <hi>England</hi> to be a standing Law, <hi>viz.</hi> That no man is to be adjudged of Life, Limb. Liberty, or Estate, but by judgement of his Peers, according to the old Law and Custom of <hi>England</hi> which is by twelve good men of his Neighbourhood; giving also liberty of exception and chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenge of five and thirty, without shewing cause, and of as many more as against whom he can shew cause, until he finde his Tryers or<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to stand indifferent; so carefully doth our good old Laws provide against all tryals by any way of arbitrary discretion.</p>
            <p>And surely that is the main standing Law of <hi>England,</hi> no English man can deny, being bound to maintain the same against any whom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soever, all Laws or Acts contrary thereunto, though made by lawful Parliaments, being null and void in themselves, and in no case ought to finde any man guilty upon any such pretended Laws.</p>
            <p>Which being undeniable Truths, these Conclusions necessarily arise
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:115760:5"/>for our information, and to be a guide unto us in Mr. <hi>Lilburn</hi>'s case.</p>
            <p n="1">1. That whatsoever <hi>John Lilburn</hi> had done against Sir <hi>Arthur Haselrig</hi> and the Commissioners at Haberdashers Hall, yea though he had slain, or wounded, or beaten, or any way scandalized or defa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med them or any of them, yet the Parliament by the Law of the Land are not his Judges or Tryers, for by that before-recited standing Law, no man is to be adjudged of Life, Limb, Liberty, or Estate, but by Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries. Yea, though <hi>John Lilburn</hi> had referred himself to them to judge him how they pleased, they ought not to have accepted thereof but to have answered, That by the ancient and standing Law of <hi>England</hi> no man ought to be tryed or judged but by Juries; and we sit not here to destroy but to preserve the true Laws of <hi>England,</hi> all other ways of tryal being in our Law unjust and arbitrary. So as it is evident then, in their judging of him themselves as they did, and not leaving him to be tryed according to Law, as they ought, their proceedings were un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawful, and to the subversion of the Fundamental Law, depriving him of his Birth-right, which is in all cases to be tryed by Juries, not otherwise.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That they did as unjustly, and as contrary to the known Laws of <hi>England,</hi> in sentencing him so severely as they did, had they been his Jury or Legal Tryers, as 7000 <hi>l.</hi> and perpetual banishment out of his native Country, whereas they know his adherence to the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament rendered him most unsecure in all parts of the world; and then to make his return Felony, is such an unparallel'd stratagem to ensnare him, that all put together, never was exceeded by any cruelty: whereas had he had tryal for the things for which they so severely cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sured him, the Jury had been bound by the Law of <hi>England</hi> to have proportiened the punishment to the offence: and how then had it been possible for then (keeping a good conscience) so to have fined a m<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> when it was impossible for them to understand him to be worth 2000 <hi>l.</hi> in all the world? or how could they have found a ground in Law to have annexed that intolerable sentence of perpetual Banish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and to have made his return Felony and death, without be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit of Clergie? No, friends, this we may see, was no Legal nor Jury<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men's work, but a partial way by discretion, where many of his ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>versaries were his Judges, and where he had no liberty of his lawful right of challenge and exception against any of them, which is the great preservative of an English-man, and without which none can be free from the malice and passion of men in power.</p>
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:115760:5"/>
            <p> So that here we see, they judging who are not his proper try<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers by the Law of the Land, and withall contrary to the known rule of the Law, censure him unjustly beyond the intent of the Law, though they had been his lawfull Jury, and make an Act contrary to the known Law of the Land, by which they intend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to render him a Felon, and take away his life.</p>
            <p>Now the unlawfulness of this Act appears herein, <hi>viz.</hi> in that it provides the capitall pun<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>shment of death without any ground in Law; for neither is it death by Law to scandalize a Parliament-man, or four or ten Committee-men, nor to break a Parliament-priviledge, nor can or ought any of these being made death or Felony, because there is no proportion between the offences and punishment, the Law of <hi>England</hi> never under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing things of that nature to be felonious, mens lives to be more precious then so in the esteem of our Law: And if the scan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalizing of Parliament-men or Committee-men is not feloni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous in our Law, surely it is not Felony for an Englishman to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn from foraign parts into his native countrey; so that this Act wanting a ground in the Law of <hi>England,</hi> and being con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary thereunto, it is cruelly and severely made, to insnare a sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gle person, for doing that which never was taken in Law to be Felony, whereby he or any man may be warned thereof, it proves it self not onely null and void, as all Acts of Parliament that are made contrary to the standing Law of <hi>England,</hi> but is a most inhumane, barbarous and bloudy Act, and such as upon which we can by no means with a safe conscience pronounce him guilty, except instead of approving our selvhs true English Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry-men, we shall prove our selves the Devills Jury-men; for we cannot pronounce him guilty, but immediately he stands as a condemned Felon, of which felonious crime our consciences do hereby quit him: So that should we do it, and he die upon it, we are his most immediate murderers; for whatever his adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>saries might aime at in all their proceedings against him, and particularly in this their bloudy act, yet the law of our Fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fathers hath so carefully placed Juries between men and death, that he cannot receive the sentence of death but upon our verdict.</p>
            <pb n="10" facs="tcp:115760:6"/>
            <p> And therefore since the Parliaments judging of him; them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves, is altogether against the Law of England.</p>
            <p>And since the scandalls of Parliament-men, nor others are fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lony, nor the breach of Parliament priviledge:</p>
            <p>Since the punishments compared to the offences, are directly contrary to the Law of England:</p>
            <p>Since that Act upon which he is prosecuted is groundlesse in the Law, and is in it self a cruell, bloody, and insnaring Act, made purposely that his life should be certainly taken away, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by his enemies abroad, or as a Felon if he returned.</p>
            <p>Since we find no felonious action to have proceeded from him in all the whole course of the Parliaments proceedings, up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on or against him, we are with an humble and sure confidence in God, to pronounce him not guilty; for what shall it profit us, either to please the malice or opinions of men, for to loose our own souls, rather let it be our choise not to fear those that can kill these bodies of ours, but to fear him who is able to cast both our bodies and souls into hell fire, from which the Lord deliver and keep us all, and from all those unjust, slight, bloody, and cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ell wayes which lead thereunto.</p>
            <p>What is or hath been done in the case of Priests and Jesuites, concernes not us, for if there be no more matter of treason a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst the Commonwealth in the ground and bottom of that Act of Parliament, which makes their coming into England treason, whereby to satisfie the consciences of those that are their Tryers, that they are Traytors, then there is in the Act for his banishment, to satisfie our consciences that he is to be found a Felon, they have a sad account to make, however not o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther mens examples, but the justnesse of our proceedings is that which will bear us out in the great and terrible day of the Lord.</p>
            <p>Nor are we in the least to be stagger'd by the common fame of his turbulency of spirit, he hath been a vehement assertor and maintainer of the good Laws and Liberties of England, and an extraordinary sufferer for his opposing all arbitrary power, and this is all for ought we know that caused him to be esteemed turbulent; nor are we to regard what his opinions are, nor what discontents have been betwixt him &amp; any man, or men, there being no difference in the Law of England, but if either wrong other,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:115760:6"/>the Law of England either is or should be open to both; what he hath said or done, either here or beyond Sea, to the prejudice or distast of any, great or small, is not now to be regarded, and how common soever the practise of men is at such trialls, and before (wanting matter in the main) to heap up aspersions by the by, such vile and inhumane practises are not to sway us in the least by way of aggravation, but having duely weighed all materiall circumstances, inducing us to make a judgment waving all other matters, either of the sins, offences or infirmities, all of which a little of true Christian charity will cover a multitude, and he that is without let him cast the first stone: of this Crime of Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lony which he standeth now charged withall, we find him not guilty; and were we or might we cast any thing into the scale to sway us to any consultation concerning him otherwise then the main matter in hand; H<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s publ<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>que good affection to the common Rights of the Nation, his many suff<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rings and distractions of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self, his wife and family, Sir <hi>Arthur Hasl<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rig</hi> seizing a great part of his livelyhood, his dangers in banishment, his confidence of the Justice of the present times; his open, clear and unconcealed casting himself upon the Justice of his Cause, and that in all meekness and humility; and his express resolution and promise of all peaceable de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meaner; all these will cry aloud to us to have a tender regard to his preservation; and we wish the present Power had been satisfied therewith, and not put him to the extremity; but he needs nothing but our Justice, the Law of <hi>England</hi> having sufficiently provided for his safety, and that we cannot, may not, nor dare not deny him, and that by us pronounceth him not gulity; and the Lord God of Heaven deliver him from all his Enemies: nor are we to be so de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luded into murder, as others have been too often in our places, as to take this bloody Act of <hi>Parliament</hi> for good and forcible, until it be repealed by another <hi>Parliament;</hi> No (God forbid) my Brethren, we should shew our selves so ignorant and unconscionable: for if we take it for good, but while we have pronounced him guilty thereupon, he stands immediately as a cond<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>mned Felon and is cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly to dye; and then what will it profit him when this Act comes to be repeal<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d? will it restore him to life again, and give him <gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he comforts of his wife and children? will it mak<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> a recomp<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nce for her heart-breaking griefs, and the sorrows of his aged Father, and
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:115760:7"/>honored Brother and Sister, and dear Friends and R<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>lations? Or will the repealing of the Act, though within an hour after his dea<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>h, acquit us from the immediate cause thereof, and of being his Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deters in the sight of God? O no, my Brethren, the rep<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>al<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ng of the Act will be to little purpose, should we be so deluded as thereupon to pronoonce him guilty. The truth is, and it is the saddest truth that b<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>longs to <hi>England,</hi> that by this deceit and false op<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nion, That Acts of Parliam<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nts are to be taken for good, and upon which Jury<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men ought to find men guilty if they have broken them, until they are repealed, all the holy men of God, that dyed as Martyrs in Queen <hi>Mary</hi>'s days, were put to death, and in plain English most hor<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ibly murdered, it being the more notorious, being done under colour of Law. And can we imagine the meer repealing of those bloody Acts are any satisfaction in the sight of God, and shall acquit those Jury<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men that found them guilty thereupon, and so opened a gap to their destruction, without which none durst have put them to death? <hi>Greenwood, Penry,</hi> and <hi>Burrow,</hi> and divers Anabaptists in Queen <hi>Elizabeths</hi> days, were also murdered upon this m<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>stake in Jury-men for non-conformity: And what satisfaction is it now that those Statutes are repealed? doth it make that they were not murdered? No, dear Friends; the greatest weight in Tryals of men lieth upon the Consciences of the Jury-men of <hi>England;</hi> they are the real Guardians of the peoples lives, limbs, liberties and estates; and they ought not to find any man guilty upon any Starue in any case, which appears to have no good ground upon the standing Law of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land:</hi> And doubtless it would become <hi>England,</hi> from the most aged and ripe years even to the youngest, yea as the Prophet <hi>Jool</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vites to him even the suckling and babes, and in the most solemn manner that may be, to keep yearly publique days of Humiliation for the many horrible Murders that have been committed by Courts of Justice and Juries; for want of which testimony of true Repent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, and of resolutions of greater care to the future, being still liable upon every temptation to do the like, no question the wrath of God hath been poured out upon the Land.</p>
            <p>And let us all pray earnestly unto God, that he will be pleas'd to give us all eys to see, and hearts to consider, how much the safety and happinesse of us all depends upon our sticking close to the old and good Lawes of the Land, and to lay to heart how
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:115760:7"/>much it concernes the good men of England the Jury-men, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>specially who are to determine all causes; to be able to judge, and to distinguish between true and counterfeit Lawes, as well in other causes as in this, least afore they are aware they take drosse for gold, and counterfeit coyn for currant money, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing deceived themselves, and deceiving others, kill where they ought to save, and of preservers become murtherers of the just and innocent: Oh let us take heed of being guided by the opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of Judges, Lawyers, pleaders, or other Officers, it is not they that must answer for our guilty or not guilty before the righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Judge of heaven and earth, before whose dreadfull Throne the prisoners at the Bar shall stand, with as much respect as any of us, or them, for God is no respecter of prrsons in Judgment.</p>
            <p>And henceforward let it be our work to make every man, woman (and child too, as far as is possible) sensible, how exceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly it concernes them to claime, and adhere to, as their un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubted right, this Fundamentall Law, <hi>That no one be adjudged of life, limb, liberty, or estate, but by Iudgment of Juries, accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the Law of the Land,</hi> and not to admit any other way of Tryalls upon any pretence whatsoever not to allow of any Law made by Parliament, contrary to any Fundamentall Law, there being no readier way to our ruine and bondage, then to submit to arbitrary or illegall practises, nothing of this world being to be more precious in our thoughts, then the Laws and Liberties of our Native Country, and which if Mr. <hi>Lilburn</hi> had enjoyed, he had never come into this danger. Most excellently to which effect is the recitall of Sir <hi>Edward Cooke</hi> upon the foremention<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed 29. chap. of <hi>Magna Charia,</hi> he saith thus:</p>
            <p>
               <q>Against <hi>the antient Fundamental Law,</hi> and in <hi>the face thereof,</hi> I find an <hi>Act of Parliament made;</hi> That as well Justices of the peace, <hi>without any finding or presentment by the Ʋerdict of twelve men,</hi> upon a bare information for the King before them made, should have full power and authority by their discretions to hear and determine all offences and contempts committed, or done by any person against the form, Ordinance, and effect of any Statute made and not repealed, by colour of which Act, <hi>shaking this Fundamentall Law;</hi> it is not credible what horrible oppressions and exactions, to the undoing of infinite numbers
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:115760:8"/>of people, were committed by Sir <hi>Richard Empson</hi> Knight, and <hi>Edward Dudley,</hi> being Justices of the peace, throughout Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land. And upon this injurious Act (as commonly in them it fall<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth out, a new Office was erected, and they made Ministers of the Kings forfeitures. But at the Pathament holden the first year of <hi>Hen.</hi> 8. this Act of the 11. of <hi>Hen.</hi> the 7. is recited and made void, and the ill successe thereof, and the <hi>fearful ends</hi> of these <hi>two Oppressors</hi> should deter others from committing the like, and should admonish <hi>Parliaments,</hi> that instead of this or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary and pretious way of Tryalls, <hi>per legem terre,</hi> they bring not in absolute and partiall Tryalls by discretion.</q>
            </p>
            <p>By which we see plainly, that <hi>Parliament Law</hi> must give place to <hi>Fundamental Law,</hi> and that where it is contrary thereunto, those that shall execute the same, are justly to be punished, as Sir <hi>Richard Empson</hi> and <hi>Dudley</hi> were, and that <hi>Parliaments</hi> have <hi>not power</hi> over <hi>Fundamental Law,</hi> and especially over this Tryall by <hi>twelve men,</hi> nor may bring in absolute and partiall Tryalls by discretion, in every of which particulars they have injured Mr. <hi>Lilburn,</hi> but we must be carefull not to prove either their <hi>Empsons</hi> or their <hi>Dudleys,</hi> as all such cannot but prove, who shall have any hand in his death upon their unlawful and cruel Act, or that shall any wayes second their bloudy intentions against him, whosoever they are, though Judges without a Jury, that shall en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour to take away this life upon the same, they are no better, if not worse then <hi>Empson</hi> and <hi>Dudley,</hi> and as <hi>Empson</hi>'s and <hi>Dudley</hi>'s may they speed, even in this Generation, and be as odious to all posterity.</p>
            <p>This <hi>good old Law</hi> Sir <hi>Edward Cooke</hi> affirmeth to be the <hi>best birth right</hi> the people have, for thereby their goods, lands, wifes, children, bodies, lives, honor, and estimation, are protected from wrong and injury; and that by this Law every one without exception for any injury done unto him, may take his remedy by the due course of the Law, and have Justice and Right done to him, freely without sale, fully without deniall, and speedily without delay, and then it is nor <hi>only Iustice,</hi> but <hi>Right:</hi> Oh when shall <hi>this Instice</hi> and <hi>this Right</hi> florish again in England, even when we are more Englishmen stablished and grounded upon
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:115760:8"/>our <hi>Fore-fathers Lawes,</hi> and not tossed to and fro with every wind of the opinions of Judges or Lawyers, and may we now begin to be such, as high time it is we should be such, and let the preservation of Mr. <hi>Lilburn</hi> by this our just and legall Verdict, declare to all men our full resolutions to be such, and that these our Laws and Rights shall be as deare and pretious for ever, as they seemed to be to the Army, when they remonstrated, <hi>That they esteemed livelyhood, and their neerest relations, a price but suffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient</hi> to the purchase of so rich a blessing, that they, and all the free-born people of England might sit down in quiet, in full possession of those antient Fundamentall Rights, without which they had little hope of enjoying any comforts of life, or so much as life it self, but at the pleasure of some men, ruling meer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly according to will and power. But let us not be <hi>yea</hi> and <hi>nay</hi> my brethren, but <hi>yea,</hi> it being good and acceptable to God to be zealous in a good matter, wherein we may comfortably hope for his gracious protection, which he never faileth to vouchsafe to such as <hi>fear an oath,</hi> and tremble at his word.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>